Finding Aid for St. David’s Episcopal Church (Garden City, Mich.) records, 1955-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
St. David’s Episcopal Church (Garden City, Mich.) records 1955-2008
St. David’s Episcopal Church (Garden City, Mich.).
2 oversize volumes
5 linear feet
0660 Ba 2
Episcopal church established in Garden City, Michigan, March 1955. The church disbanded in May 2005 due to dwindling attendance. The church was briefly reformed as the Journey of Faith church. The record group contains records documenting the parish's admission to the Diocese of Michigan, records supporting anniversary celebrations, vestry meeting minutes, financial reports, vestry handbooks, annual reports, parochial reports, a ten-year statistical report (1992-2002), loan and grant documentation, calling committee correspondence and reports, nursery school teacher contracts, ministry team records, Trike-a-thon documentation, parish directories and a membership card catalog. There are also church registers detailing baptisms, marriages, burials, communicants, and similar information, and registers of church services with attendance information. The records have been arranged into the following series: History; Vestry Meeting Minutes and Financial Reports; Administration; Membership; Parish registers; and Registers of Services.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (donor no. 1059 ) came to the library in 2005 as part of the archives of the Episcopal Church, Diocese of Michigan. Additions have been received.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
St. David's Episcopal Church was established on Passion Sunday, March 27th, 1955 as a parochial mission of Christ Episcopal Church of Dearborn. The Very Reverend Jon Weaver, Dean of St. Paul's Cathedral, Detroit, MI, presided. Services were held in the gymnasium of the Garden City Memorial School until 1957, when the congregation broke ground for the construction of a new church home at 27500 Marquette.
The parish was admitted to union with the Diocese of Michigan on May 15th, 1964, ending its role as a parochial mission of Christ Episcopal Church, Dearborn, MI. On November 29th, 1964, the Very Reverend Thomas Smith installed the Reverend Fred Nicholson as the first Rector of St. David's.
The Congregation was dissolved on May 15th, 2005. Leadership cited dwindling attendance aggravated by the 2003 General Convention's consent to the election of Gene Robinson as Bishop in New Hampshire. The congregation's attendance had dwindled from an average of 300 in 1965 to about 35 per week by the end of 2003. The remaining congregation reinvented itself as the Journey of Faith Church and moved to a new location at the Garden City Maplewood Community Center.
Church Leadership
Lay Minister
1955-1960 Mr. Arthur D. Thomas
Vicar
1956-1963 Rev. Fred Nicholson
Rectors
1964-1968 Rev. Fred Nicholson
1968-1970 Rev. John E. Blewett
1970-1973 Rev. Robert V. Burrows
1973-1989 Rev. Ralph G. McGimpsey
1989-2005 Rev. Mark A. Jenkins
St. David's Episcopal Church, located in Garden City, MI, was established in 1955 and disbanded in 2005. The record group contains records documenting the parish's admission to the Diocese of Michigan, the contents of a scrapbook, records supporting anniversary celebrations, vestry meeting minutes, financial reports, vestry handbooks, annual reports, parochial reports, a ten-year statistical report (1992-2002), loan and grant documentation, calling committee correspondence and reports, nursery school teacher contracts, ministry team records, Trike-a-thon documentation, parish directories and a membership card catalog. The records have been arranged into the following series: History; Vestry Meeting Minutes and Financial Reports; Parish Registers and related; Register of Services; Membership; and Administration.
Subjects:
St. David's Episcopal Church (Garden City, Mich.); Journey of Faith Church (Dearborn, Mich.); Garden City (Mich.)--Church history.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Garden City.; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Garden City.
- History
  The History series (1955-1985) includes records documenting the admission of the parish to the Diocese of Michigan in 1964, the contents of a scrapbook maintained by the church, and records supporting 20th, 25th, and 30th anniversary celebrations. The scrapbook and anniversary series contain newspaper clippings and photographs.
  - Admission of Parish 1964 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook 1955-1959 (Box 1)
  - Anniversaries
    - 20th Anniversary 1975 (Box 1)
    - 25th Anniversary 1980 (Box 1)
    - 30th Anniversary 1985 (Box 1)
- Vestry Meeting Minutes and Financial Reports
  The Vestry /Meeting Minutes and Financial Report series (1955-2008) contains Vestry/ Rector's Committee meeting minutes, financial reports, and Vestry handbooks.
  - Meeting minutes and financial reports 1955-1962, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Financial reports 1963 (Box 1)
  - Meeting minutes and financial reports 1964 (Box 1)
  - Financial reports 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Meeting minutes and financial reports 1967-1986, 12 folders (Box 1)
  - Meeting minutes and financial reports 1986-2002, 9 folders (Box 2)
  - Vestry record book 2002-2003, 2 folders (Box 2)
    (include agenda and minutes, treasurer's reports, other reports, etc.)
  - Vestry Handbooks 2003-2005, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Vestry meeting files 2005, July 2007-February 2008, 10 folders (Box 2)
- Membership
  The Membership series (1955-2005) includes a set of parish directories (1969-1995) and a membership card catalog. There are a few years missing from the set of parish directories. This series also includes transfer of membership forms.
  - Parish Directories 1969-1995, 2003-2005 (Box 3)
  - Letters of transfer, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Membership card catalog 1955-2005 (Box 3)
- Parish Registers and related
  The Parish Registers and related materials series (1955-2002) includes records of baptisms, burials, marriages, communicants, and confirmations. Also includes are the completed forms with information about baptisms, marriages, and burials.
  - Register no. 1: Communicants October 1955-January 1960; Baptisms, May 1955-June 1960; Confirmations, January 1956-June 1958; Burials, May 1957-July 1960 (Box 4)
  - Register no. 2: Communicants June 1960-August, 1973; Baptisms, July 1960-December 1977; Confirmations, April 1959-January 1972; Burials, September 1960-August 1990; Marriages, June 1961-April 1982 (Volume 1)
  - Register no. 3: Communicants May 1974-June 1989; Baptisms, December 1977-May 1990; Confirmations, February 1970-December 1974; Marriages, May 1982-October 1985 (Box 4)
  - Register no. 4: Confirmations April 1976-November 1990 (Box 4)
  - Register no. 5: Marriages November 1985-June 2002 (Box 4)
  - Register no. 6: Baptisms May 1990-September 2001; Confirmations, 1996-2001 (Volume 2)
  - Baptismal information forms (Box 4)
  - Funeral and burial information (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous marriage information (Box 4)
- Register of Services
  The Registers of Services series (1955-2008) contains information about the weekly services, including attendance, number of communicants, etc.
  - March 1955-August 1962 (Box 4)
  - August 1962-July 1965 (Box 4)
  - July 1965-February 1971 (Box 4)
  - February 1971-March 1977 (Box 4)
  - March 1977-March 1988 (Box 4)
  - March 1988-May 2005 (Box 4)
  - May 2005-February 2008 (Box 4)
  - 2003-2008 (print-outs) (Box 4)
- Administration
  The Administrative series (1955-2007) contains annual reports, parochial reports, loan and grant applications and supporting documents, records of search committees, nursery school teacher contracts, ministry team records, and Trike-a-thon event documentation.
  - Annual Reports 1957-2004, 9 folders (Box 5)
  - Parochial reports 1955-2007, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Parish statistical report for 1992-2002, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Policy manual (Box 5)
  - Loans and grants 1966-1999 (Box 5)
  - Calling committee records 1967-1989, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Nursery school teacher contracts 1990-1993 (Box 5)
  - Ministry team records 2003 (Box 5)
  - Trike-a-thon event 1993-1997 (Box 5)
  - Transition 2003 (Box 5)